Tibet
Marist Archives and Special Collections
- Tibet, 2.1.3.5
  - Out of This World: Across the Himalayas to Forbidden Tibet by Lowell Thomas, Jr. [illustrations], 1949; 5 (Box 1535)
    - Caption: [page 113] All plowing in Tibet is done with yaks and wooden plows. In spite of the country's mountainous nature there is more than enough arable land. The need, in view of the declining population, is for more plow hands, 16
    - Caption: [page 115] Tricky going for the horses as Dad leads the way into the Red Idol Gorge near Saugang. Hardly a day of our journey to Lhasa passed without a struggle with mountain streams in floods brought on by the monsoon, 17
    - Caption: [page 119] At Gyantse, another exchange of silk scarves and more ancient eggs as gifts from the Tibetan trade agent, Khenchung Lama (center), who wears a gown of golden silk brocaded with dragons, and a golden hat, 18
    - Verso: Verso: Welcomed by the Monk Tromo Trochi of Gyantse, 18-verso
    - Caption: [page 119] At Gyantse, another exchange of silk scarves and more ancient eggs as gifts from the Tibetan trade agent, Khenchung Lama (center), who wears a gown of golden silk brocaded with dragons, and a golden hat, 19
    - Caption: [page 119] At Gyantse, another exchange of silk scarves and more ancient eggs as gifts from the Tibetan trade agent, Khenchung Lama (center), who wears a gown of golden silk brocaded with dragons, and a golden hat, 20
    - Caption: [page 119] At Gyantse, another exchange of silk scarves and more ancient eggs as gifts from the Tibetan trade agent, Khenchung Lama (center), who wears a gown of golden silk brocaded with dragons, and a golden hat, 21
    - Caption: [page 119] At Gyantse, another exchange of silk scarves and more ancient eggs as gifts from the Tibetan trade agent, Khenchung Lama (center), who wears a gown of golden silk brocaded with dragons, and a golden hat, 22
    - Caption: [page 129] Tsewong Norbu, the cook, performed miracles over yak-dung fires, with the assistance of our primus stove-foxhole type. Here he is preparing dinner in a Tibetan kitchen, where our stove was a fascinating innovation, 23
    - Caption: [page 131] These smiling women are engaged in an important domestic task-churning yak butter tea in a wooden cylinder. The ingredients are: tea leaves, soda, boiling water and large chunks of yak butter. The mixture is soupy Verso: Making yak-buttered tea - in a peasant's home, 24
    - Verso: Making yak-buttered tea - in a peasant's home, 24-verso
    - Caption: [page 131] These smiling women are engaged in an important domestic task-churning yak butter tea in a wooden cylinder. The ingredients are: tea leaves, soda, boiling water and large chunks of yak butter. The mixture is soupy, 25
    - Caption: [page 133] By whirling a prayer wheel like this, a Tibetan grandfather acquires merit for his credit in a future life. Inside the silver cylinder are Buddhist prayers, on parchment. This is a popular way of praying in Tibet, 26
    - Verso: Tibetan grandfather wins merit by spinning prayer wheel, 26-verso
    - Caption: [page 133] By whirling a prayer wheel like this, a Tibetan grandfather acquires merit for his credit in a future life. Inside the silver cylinder are Buddhist prayers, on parchment. This is a popular way of praying in Tibet, 27
    - Verso: Old man spinning prayer wheel, 27-verso
    - Caption: [page 133] By whirling a prayer wheel like this, a Tibetan grandfather acquires merit for his credit in a future life. Inside the silver cylinder are Buddhist prayers, on parchment. This is a popular way of praying in Tibet, 28
    - Caption: [page 135] One of the tasks of a Tibetan peasant wife is to operate a hand loom, on which the family clothing is spun. Here the weaver attends to her work, indifferent to the camera; the men of the household are in the fields, 29
    - Verso: Weaving in a Tibetan home., 29-verso
    - Caption: [page 135] One of the tasks of a Tibetan peasant wife is to operate a hand loom, on which the family clothing is spun. Here the weaver attends to her work, indifferent to the camera; the men of the household are in the fields, 30
    - Verso: "One of the tasks of a Tibetan peasant wife is to operate a hand loom, on which the family clothing is spun ", 30-verso
    - Caption: [page 139] Near the pass we met a caravan of yaks. At some narrow places on the Tibetan trails a collision of two caravans would be disastrous, and to avoid this danger the animals wear bels to warn travelers approaching, 31
    - Verso: "Near the pass (Karo-la, nearly 17,000') we meet a caravan of yaks ", 31-verso
    - [3 copies] Caption: [page 143] Which is the shaggier, this Tibetan peasant or his two Apsos? Dogs, most of them wild and vicious, are the scavengers of Tibet-along with vultures and ravens. But the Apsos, as seen here, are pets among the people, 32
    - Note: A typical Tibetan of the high plateau with a pair of Apsos, 33
  - Tibet: Out of This World: Across the Himalayas to Forbidden Tibet by Lowell Thomas, Jr. [illustrations], 1949; 6 (Box 1535)
    - Caption: [pages 144-145] Gowned in yellow with long ceremonial sleeves. These are three of the most influential men in Tibet. They are members of the Kashag, the most important of the Dalai Lama's three cabinets, 1
    - Verso: This highest cabinet is called "Kashag" - two lay ministers and their head, a lama, in the middle, 1-verso
    - Caption: [pages 144-145] Ready for the summer festival, this Tibetan woman wears a silk dress, a turquoise-studded hat, 2
    - [2 copies] Caption: [page 147] A peasant girl brings home the bacon-in this case a butchered sheep. Buddhist doctrine forbids killing animals and eating their meat, but in Tibet an exception to the rule is made in the case of sheep and yak, 3
    - Caption: [page 150] "Hello!" A mail carrier sticks out his tongue in the customary greeting, a mark of Tibetan politeness. The spear is his badge of office. From time to time these carriers bore out our tape recordings for broadcasts, 4
    - Caption: [page 151] At Pedi, our caravan enters the muddy courtyard of the headman's home. While the animals wait to be unloaded, the camera catches them and the battered remnants of an old fort, rising on a hill in the background, 5
    - Caption: [page 155] Landing at Chusul, on the Tsangpo, or upper Brahmaputra, which flows at a height of twelve thousand feet. The yak-skin coracle, or kowa, can carry a load weighing more than a ton, yet is itself amazingly light, 6
    - Caption: [page 157] Our boatman, oars in hand and prayer flags on his right. Aboard is the sheep which will carry his personal belongings back upstream, while he will carry the boat-just as American Indians used to make a portage, 7
    - [2 copies] Caption: [page 158] The tiny donkeys were up to their big ears in water, but they stayed on the trail. In this method of transportation it is easy to get a load wet, but our film was carried by porters over the worst spots to keep it dry, 8
    - [2 copies] Caption: [159] Because of high waters in the valley of the Kyi Chu (the Kyi River) it took our caravan two and a half days to travel the last forty miles on the journey to Lhasa. Pack animals can't be hurried over rocks and mud, 9
    - Caption: [page 161] Our sirdar-third figure from the right-gestures to direct the caravan. On many a day during our journey he and his slow-moving pack animals didn't reach their destination until after dark, but they always arrived, 10
    - [2 copies] Caption: [page 165] Looking out over the broad expanse of the Kyi Chu. I am carrying my 16-mm. magazine-loading camera. (I also had a smaller 16-mm. camera as a spare, a Rolleiflex for black-and-whites, a Leica for kodachromes.), 11
    - Verso: L.T., Jr. on rock, looking out over Brahmaputra, 11-verso
    - Caption: [page 169] A Tibetan noblewoman and her son, wearing some of the colorful costumes seen in the Holy City during the summer festival. Ladies like striped skirts, with the stripes in the material seldom if ever matching, 12
    - Verso: Tibetan Noble woman and son wearing some of the colorful costumes seen in the Holy City during the summer festival, 12-verso
    - Caption: [page 171] As soon as we had unloaded our caravan at Treda Linga, Dorje Changwaba arrived with these presents of food from his government: sacks of grain, for our animals and, for us, eggs, mutton, and vegetables, 13
    - Caption: [page 175] Actors on stage at the Dalai Lama's summer palace were shaded by a roof of canvas decorated with geometrical designs. The audience, almost as much concerned with our presence as with the drama, turned to see us, 14
    - [2 copies] Caption: [page 179] From left to right: our sponsor, Tsipon Shakabpa, a monk, an official called Rimshi Kyipup, L. T., Sr., and Dorje Changwaba. Tsipon Shakabpa is one of the very few Tibetans who have traveled in the outside world, 15
    - Verso: Our Lhasa hosts: Tsepon Shakabpa, Rimshi Kyipup and Dorje Changwaba, 15-verso
    - [2 copies] Caption: [page 181] In a special drill for our party, Tibetan soldiers march past, some with British gear left over from World War I. These troops reflect the need for modern weapons if Tibetan forces are to hold off the Chinese Reds, 16
  - Out of This World: Across the Himalayas to Forbidden Tibet by Lowell Thomas, Jr. [illustrations], 1949; 7 (Box 1535)
    - Caption: [page 182] Watched by serious-eyed children, Dad shops for gifts in the bazaar at Lhasa. The Moslem merchant is a member of the only minority group in the country; his people have long lived in friendship with the Tibetans, 1
    - Verso: Lhasa streetshop, L.T. holdin beads, 1-verso
    - [2 copies] Caption: [page 183] Furs, horseshoes and iron tools are among the items for sale in the Lhasa bazaar. With the possible exception of the furs, all these products have been brought in over the mountain passes, from beyond the Himalayas, 2
    - Verso: White skins at outside street shop, 2-verso
    - [4 copies] Caption: [page 185] In a Moslem shop in the bazaar at Lhasa, Dorje Changwaba and L. T. Sr., listen to an Indian recording of Tibetan music. The owner of the store stands behind Dorje. At the far right, hand on the door, is Norbu, our cook, 3
    - [4 copies] Caption: [page 187] A Lhasa policeman, distinguished by a floppy felt hat, western style, and a single dangling earring. We were told that these officers of the law are about the only people ever to be murdered in the Tibetan capital, 4
    - Caption: [page 189] On the roof of the Jokang, the cathedral that is the holiest place in all Tibet, a monk poses with prayer wheel and rosary while a grinning young acolyte stands by. The Jokang is famous for its jewel-studded Buddha, 5
    - Verso: On the roof of the Jokang[?], the cathederal that is the holiest place in all Tibet, a monk poses with prayer wheel and rosary while a gummij[?] young acolyte stands by. The Jokang is famous for its jewel-studded Buddha, 5-verso
    - [3 copies] Caption: [page 190] Dad enjoys a rare bath in Dorje Changwaba's tin tub on the roof at Treda Linga. This was a much-appreciated luxury. On the trail to Lhasa what bathing we did was in icy water from snowy mountain heights, 6
    - Verso: L.T. enjoys a rare bath at the home of Mr. dorje Changwaba in Treda Linga, on the road to Lhasa, Tibet, 6-verso
    - Caption: [page 197] Weird carved and painted masks and skulls adorn the doorway of the State Oracle's private monastery. The Oracle is consulted on all matters of political importance and, in trance, he foretells coming events, 7
    - of the State Oracle's private monastery. The Oracle is consulted on all matters of political importance and, in trance, he foretells coming events, 7-verso
    - [5 copies]Caption: [page 199] The State Oracle. We did not witness one of his trances. It is said that the only person capable of understanding what the young man predicts during a spell is his secretary, a special government official, 8
    - Verso: Oracle smiling, 8-verso
    - Caption: [page 203] Wearing the gold peaked cap that is his crown, the Dalai Lama smiles down from his throne, where he receives and blesses pilgrims. This photograph of His Holiness with a smile on his face is a very rare one, 9
    - [3 copies] Caption: [page 205] Here is a formal portrait of His Holiness, who will assume absolute power over Tibet when he comes of age in 1952. Beside the throne, members of his household; behind the pillar, the Lord Chamberlain, 10
    - [2 copies]Caption: [page 209] To accommodate our cameras, the living God of Mercy stepped from the shadows of the dark throne room into a shaft of sunlight. The Dalai Lama, without his peaked ceremonial hat, is second from right, 11
    - Verso: The Dalai Lama, 4th from Lowell Thomas, Sr. on left, 11-verso
    - Caption: [page 212] Three small-fry relatives of the Dalai Lama pose for us outside the palace. They are, from left to right, Kando Tsiring and Tenzin Ngawang, niece and nephew, and Jizon Pama, the ruler's sister, 12
    - Caption: [page 213] The Norbu Linga players enact a heroic drama at the home of the Dalai Lama's family. During the summer festival, masked actors such as these perform without pause from seven in the morning until late afternoon, 13
    - [4 copies] Caption: [page 215] The narrator of the drama wears a white mask. The dancing, singing and clashing of cymbals throughout the day-long performance are interrupted periodically while he tells the story in a ceremonial chant, 14
  Box 1536
- Tibet, 2.1.3.5
  - Tibet: Out of This World: Across the Himalayas to Forbidden Tibet by Lowell Thomas, Jr. [illustrations], 1949; 1 (Box 1536)
    - Caption: [page 217] Using chopsticks as in China, we lunch at the Foreign Office, Lhasa, with five Tibetan statesmen. Mail and papers are "filed," in Tibet, by hanging them in bunches like prayer flags, from walls, pillars and door posts, 1
    - Verso: Luncheon at the Foreign Office with group of high officials. Note filing system dangling from ceiling; Luncheon - Foreign Office, Group look at camera, 1-verso
    - Caption: [page 217] Using chopsticks as in China, we lunch at the Foreign Office, Lhasa, with five Tibetan statesmen. Mail and papers are "filed," in Tibet, by hanging them in bunches like prayer flags, from walls, pillars and door posts, 2
    - Caption: [page 217] Using chopsticks as in China, we lunch at the Foreign Office, Lhasa, with five Tibetan statesmen. Mail and papers are "filed," in Tibet, by hanging them in bunches like prayer flags, from walls, pillars and door posts, 3
    - Caption: [page 217] Using chopsticks as in China, we lunch at the Foreign Office, Lhasa, with five Tibetan statesmen. Mail and papers are "filed," in Tibet, by hanging them in bunches like prayer flags, from walls, pillars and door posts, 4
    - Caption: [page 219] On the Roof of the World, as elsewhere, dice games are popular. Here the gamblers have been momentarily interrupted. When playing, they slap the dice cup onto the leather board with a thud and a shout for luck, 5
    - Caption: [page 221] Two village women hold offerings for the gods-barley, flour and butter-which they will leave at the chorten behind them. Dressed in their best, they wear bracelets and headdress ornaments of coral and seed pearls, 6
    - Verso: Two village women hold offerings for the gods-barley, flour and butter-which they will leave at the chorten behind them. Dressed in their best, they wear bracelets and headdress ornaments of coral and seed pearls, 6-verso
    - Caption: [page 223] Tibetan nomads, husband and wife. Polyandry is prevalent among these people and it is common for a wife to be married to her husband's brothers. This woman looks as though she has smallpox scars, 7
    - Verso: "Tibetan nomads, husband + wife ", 7-verso
    - Caption: [page 225] Yaks move with majestic slowness over a stony Tibetan field. We found no tractors in the Forbidden Land, and agriculture is where it was centuries ago. Notice the method of harnessing, with ropes of yak hair, 8
    - Caption: [page 225] Yaks move with majestic slowness over a stony Tibetan field. We found no tractors in the Forbidden Land, and agriculture is where it was centuries ago. Notice the method of harnessing, with ropes of yak hair, 9
    - Caption: [page 225] Yaks move with majestic slowness over a stony Tibetan field. We found no tractors in the Forbidden Land, and agriculture is where it was centuries ago. Notice the method of harnessing, with ropes of yak hair, 10
    - Caption: [page 227] Two young nobles. "George" Tsarong and Jigme Tering, pose for photographs with their wives. "George's" wife, the girl on the right, does not speak any English. The other three went to school in India, 11
    - Verso: Rimchi Jigme Taring, second from left; his bro. [brother] and their wives who are mother and daughter. He gave up throne of Sikkim to remain a country gentleman in Tibet, 11-verso
    - Caption: [page 227] Two young nobles. "George" Tsarong and Jigme Tering, pose for photographs with their wives. "George's" wife, the girl on the right, does not speak any English. The other three went to school in India Verso: Rimchi Jigme Taring, second from left; his bro. [brother] and their wives who are mother and daughter. He gave up throne of Sikkim to remain a country gentleman in Tibet, 12
    - Verso: Two young Tibet noblemen of Lhasa and their wives, 12-verso
    - Caption: [page 227] Two young nobles. "George" Tsarong and Jigme Tering, pose for photographs with their wives. "George's" wife, the girl on the right, does not speak any English. The other three went to school in India Verso: Rimchi Jigme Taring, second from left; his bro. [brother] and their wives who are mother and daughter. He gave up throne of Sikkim to remain a country gentleman in Tibet, 13
    - Verso: Two young Tibet noblemen of Lhasa and their wives, 13-verso
    - Caption: [page 227] Two young nobles. "George" Tsarong and Jigme Tering, pose for photographs with their wives. "George's" wife, the girl on the right, does not speak any English. The other three went to school in India Verso: Rimchi Jigme Taring, second from left; his bro. [brother] and their wives who are mother and daughter. He gave up throne of Sikkim to remain a country gentleman in Tibet, 14
    - Caption: [page 229] On the roof of the Medical College, Dad and I make a recording of the sound of a Tibetan trumpet. Visible across the valley are the golden roofs of the Potala, with the mountains seen rising in the distance beyond, 15
    - Caption: [page 231] Inside a temple at the Medical College, on Chakpori Hill, lamaist gods look out over offerings which include a row of vessels filled with water. In the foreground, a yak butter lamp; overhead, scarves given by pilgrims, 16
    - Caption: [page 231] Inside a temple at the Medical College, on Chakpori Hill, lamaist gods look out over offerings which include a row of vessels filled with water. In the foreground, a yak butter lamp; overhead, scarves given by pilgrims, 17
    - Caption: [page 235] The Vatican of Tibet, the Potala, rises nine hundred feet above the Lhasa plain. This view of it, clearly reflected in reverse in the still water of the foreground, we saw each morning from our quarters at Treda Linga, 18
    - Caption: [page 237] Photographed at the home of Tsipon Shakabpa: from left to right, Dorje Changwaba; Ponda Tsang, a wealthy Tibetan trader; next, an unknown monk, with Tsipon Shakabpa, Dad and our host's two sons, 19
    - Caption: [page 237] Photographed at the home of Tsipon Shakabpa: from left to right, Dorje Changwaba; Ponda Tsang, a wealthy Tibetan trader; next, an unknown monk, with Tsipon Shakabpa, Dad and our host's two sons, 20
    - Caption: [page 237] Photographed at the home of Tsipon Shakabpa: from left to right, Dorje Changwaba; Ponda Tsang, a wealthy Tibetan trader; next, an unknown monk, with Tsipon Shakabpa, Dad and our host's two sons, 21
    - Verso: Group at home of Tsipon Shakabpa. Host and two small sons next to L.T., 21-verso
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] The aged abbots of Drepung Gompa, flanked by two heavily padded proctors with gold-ornamented staffs. These monastery heads greatly influence government, 22
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] The aged abbots of Drepung Gompa, flanked by two heavily padded proctors with gold-ornamented staffs. These monastery heads greatly influence government, 23
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] The aged abbots of Drepung Gompa, flanked by two heavily padded proctors with gold-ornamented staffs. These monastery heads greatly influence government, 24
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] In the noisy Lhasa bazaar, exotic oriental items are sold side by side with such western gewgaws as sunglasses, mirrors, and pencils, brought by caravan, 25
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] In the noisy Lhasa bazaar, exotic oriental items are sold side by side with such western gewgaws as sunglasses, mirrors, and pencils, brought by caravan, 26
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] In the courtyard of a Lhasa monastery, a monk spins one of the prayer wheels, stuffed with thousands of written prayers, that relay devout wishes to Buddha, 27
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] In the courtyard of a Lhasa monastery, a monk spins one of the prayer wheels, stuffed with thousands of written prayers, that relay devout wishes to Buddha, 28
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] In the courtyard of a Lhasa monastery, a monk spins one of the prayer wheels, stuffed with thousands of written prayers, that relay devout wishes to Buddha, 29
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Tibetan abbeys contain many jewel-studded figures such as this grotesque one, which is at the great Drepung monastery, 30
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Inside a Sera temple, the monks are assembled at midday. A proctor (center) stands by while a lama recites prayers. Note gold images in the background, 31
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Inside a Sera temple, the monks are assembled at midday. A proctor (center) stands by while a lama recites prayers. Note gold images in the background, 32
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Inside a Sera temple, the monks are assembled at midday. A proctor (center) stands by while a lama recites prayers. Note gold images in the background, 33
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Inside a Sera temple, the monks are assembled at midday. A proctor (center) stands by while a lama recites prayers. Note gold images in the background, 34
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Inside a Sera temple, the monks are assembled at midday. A proctor (center) stands by while a lama recites prayers. Note gold images in the background, 35
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Inside a Sera temple, the monks are assembled at midday. A proctor (center) stands by while a lama recites prayers. Note gold images in the background, 36
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Inside a Sera temple, the monks are assembled at midday. A proctor (center) stands by while a lama recites prayers. Note gold images in the background, 37
  - Tibet: Out of This World: Across the Himalayas to Forbidden Tibet by Lowell Thomas, Jr. [illustrations], 1949; 2 (Box 1536)
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Dad in an improvised sedan chair at Gyantse. Dr. Pal stands at left and garrison commander, Captain Patil, at right, 1
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Dad in an improvised sedan chair at Gyantse. Dr. Pal stands at left and garrison commander, Captain Patil, at right, 2
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Dad in an improvised sedan chair at Gyantse. Dr. Pal stands at left and garrison commander, Captain Patil, at right, 3
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Dad and the rescue team. Front row: Indian Major A. K. bose, nurse Emily Bateman, Dad, Roy Bisbee. Rear, right: Dr. Pal, 4
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Dad and the rescue team. Front row: Indian Major A. K. bose, nurse Emily Bateman, Dad, Roy Bisbee. Rear, right: Dr. Pal, 5